出了原来的Vue生态系统
out of the original Vue ecosystem
这是我打算击败的
that I intended to beat
而我当时超级高兴地看到
and I'm super happy then at
它能够成为今天的样子
it is able to become what it is today
所以有太多的人
so too many people who are
刚开始接触vite的人
just getting on to vite
vite可能仍然觉得是一个新的闪亮的玩具 但
vite may still feel like a new in shiny toy but
你可能不知道的是 它
what you probably don't know is it's
实际上已经是2和1
actually already 2 and 1/2 years oak
所以在这次演讲中 我将分享一些历史
so in this talk I'm going to share some history
关于它的起源
on its origins
但在我们谈及它的起源之前
but before we talk about its origins
人们可能会问 什么是饲料
one may ask the question what is feed
最初的想法是什么 使我
what was the original idea that made me
开始研究它的主要原因
major start working on it
很多人都问过我这个问题
many people have asked me that question
我总是觉得有点难以解释
and I've always found it a little difficult to explain
简而言之 我们在码头上的口号是下一代的
concisely our tagline on the docks is next generation
前端工具
front end tooling
这
which
实际上 对于非前端开发者来说 这并不能说明什么
actually doesn't say much to non front end developers
事实上
in fact
在黑客新闻上有一整条线在抱怨
that was a whole thread on hacker news complaining
所以一方面
about it so on one hand
这是因为
this is because
前端工具这个词
the term front end tooling
带有很多的历史负担
carries a lot of historical burden
你需要知道这些年来前端工具是如何发展的
you need to know how front n has evolved over the years
来理解我们正在处理什么样的问题
to understand what kind of problems we're dealing with
以及为什么我们首先需要Bill工具
and why we need Bill toolings in the first place
另一方面 这些自己的
on the other hand these own
范围 它的
scope it's
它的任务或它的预期用例
mission or its intended use case
随着时间的推移 也有了很大的发展和变化
has also evolved and changed quite a bit over time
对 所以
right so
让我们回到
let's go back
让我们回到预先建立的工具时代 想想我们如何
to the pre built tool days and think about how we
写网页
wrote web pages
在没有任何形式的工具参与之前 对吗？
before there were any sort of tooling involved right
我们在页面中加入爵士乐的唯一方法是
the only way for us to include jazzground the page is
通过使用一个脚本标签
by using a script tag
而所有这些jawscript都是隐式评估的
and all these jawscript are implicitly evaluated
在共享的全局范围内
in the shared global scope
所以
so
默认的工作方式是
the default way of working was
把所有的东西都写在一个
just writing everything in a single
大文件 所以当AB变得更加复杂时
big file so when the AB gets more complex
单个文件显然会变得笨重
a single file obviously gets unwieldy
所以我们开始把东西分成小文件
so we start breaking things up into smaller files
那时的javascript还没有模块
javascript didn't have modules back then
所以所有这些文件
so all these files
仍然隐含地共享同一个全局范围
still implicitly share the same global scope
有时我们会
and sometimes we would
做一些事情 比如ife
do things like ife
这样的事情会立即涉及到函数表达式
immediately involved function expressions
这有点像一个内联的
this is kind of like an inline
范围
scope
所以有点像一个模块 你知道
so kind of like a module you know
但
but
但我们仍然要通过全局范围进行交流
we still have to communicate through the global scope
将东西附加到一个窗口
attaching things to a window
和
and
如果你看一下一些早期库的源代码
if you look at some of the source code of
早期的库
early day libraries
我们实际上使用了非常简单的
we actually use very simple
脚本将大量的ifes串联起来
scripts to concatenate a lot of these ifes together
这就是为什么你会看到前面有分号的原因
which is why you will see that semicolon in the front
以避免
to just avoid
连接的ifes被
to concatenated ifes being
认为是在调用前面的表达式
considered calling the previous expression
而后
and then
早期 像dojo和yui的出现
early for emerges like dojo and yui
开始实现他们自己的运行时模块加载器
started implementing their own runtime module loaders
有人试图将这个东西标准化为AMD
there was an attempt to standardize this thing to AMD
它代表了异步模块定义
which stands for asynchronous module definition
你们中的一些人可能曾经使用过这个
some of you might have used this before
并要求js使用AMD的运行时加载器
and required js with the runtime loader for AMD
的运行时加载器 所以从今天开始回过头来看 其实是很有意思的
so it's actually interesting to look back from
今天 因为requirement js正在加载
today becauserequire js was loading
并在开发过程中对模块进行转换
and transforming modules on the fly during development
你实际上可以购买插件
you can actually buy pluggings
来实现代码的快速转换
to transpire code on the fly
而且它还提供了一个优化工具
and it also provided a optimized tool
基本上是构建命令
essentially the build command
来构建一个用于生产的项目
to build a project for production
而且它是在没有js 0点的情况下编写的
and it was written with no js 0 point for something
所以这实际上是非常酷的
so this was actually really cool
因为这听起来很像他今天的爆发方式
because it sounds quite like how he burst today
对 这里最大的区别是 require
right the big difference here is that require
GS在很大程度上仍然是一个错误的时间工具
GS is still largely a wrong time tool
所有的转换
all the transformation
实际上是在浏览器端发生的
actually happens in the browser side
因此 一个很大的限制是 我们可以对代码做什么样的转换
so a great limit what kind of transformers
我们可以对我们的代码做什么
we can do to our code
的区别
and the difference between
之间的区别
between the optimization
工具和错误的时间行为之间的区别
tool and the wrong time behavior
之间的差别还是很明显的
is still quite stark
因为有些事情是不切实际的
because some of the things is just impractical to do
当你
when you
浏览器中 当你把它运送到生产中去的时候
in the browser when you ship it to production
对 所以后来
right so then
nojs出现了 并且炸开了锅
nojs came along and blew up
而common js成为
and common js became
成为了乔纳森广场模块的事实标准
the de facto standard for Jonathan square modules
这种影响一直持续到今天
and the effect still lingers today
你仍然可以看到很多库
you still see a lot of libraries
只提供 common js 或 umd
only shipping common js or umd
而人们开始
and people started
想在浏览器中使用nojs包
wanting to use nojs packages in the browser
而且他们还希望在浏览器和nojs代码中使用相同的模块格式
and they also want to use the same module format
浏览器和nojs代码都使用相同的模块格式
for both the browser and nojs code
他们想在所有地方使用通用js
they want to use common js everywhere
所以
so
人们发明了模块管家
people invented module butlers
比如browserify和webpack
like browserify and webpack
采纳了我们的住宿模块 并将它们结合起来
took our accommodations modules and combine them
形成一个单一的捆绑
into a single bundle
其中的立场
which stand
被包括在你的脚本网球的实际页面上
gets included on the actual page for your script tennis
所以这些填充工具也提供了强大的插件
so these fill tools also provided powerful plugging
和加载器的磁性
and loader magnetisms
而我当时是在2013年刚刚开始从事视图工作的
and I was just started working on view back then in
那是非常早的事情
and that was super early
后来我就有了单文件组件的想法
and later on I had this idea of single file components
一种定义组件及其模板的格式
a format that defines a component with its template
样式中的脚本
script from style
在一个单一的文件中
in a single file
你可能对这个很熟悉 如果你是
you're probably familiar with this if you're
你用过view或spelt
you've used view or spelt
我意识到有可能
I realized it was possible to
编写加载器 将这种格式转换成
write loaders that transform this format
变成播放的工作脚本
into playing jobscript
对
right
和
and
而且
that
编译的费用也将
also the cost of the compilation would
只是在比尔时间
be at Bill time only
它不会影响运行时的性能
it won't affect the runtime performance
它不会影响生产中的性能
it won't affect the performance in production
所以
so
我写了一个单文件的视图组件
I wrote the view single file component
为浏览器火和湿包进行转换
transforms for both browser fi and wet pack
所以浏览器的火叫vo fi
so for browser fire was called vo fi
而对于wet pack 它被称为view lawyer
and for wet pack it's called view lawyer
这对早期采用者来说效果很好 所以我创建了
this worked quite well for early adopters so I created
礼物模板 所以
gift templates so
基本上只有两个git仓库
essentially just 2 git repos
人们必须克隆它们
people have to clone them
然后在本地安装独立
then installed independence locally
根据自己的喜好调整配置
tweak the configuration to their liking
然后 他们最终得到了一个可以工作的项目
then eventually they get a project working
所以这对早期采用者来说是非常好的
so this worked great for early adopters
那些
people who are
可以接受新工具的人
okay with just adopting new tools
自己想办法配置bunglers的人
figuring how to configure bunglers themselves
但对于一般开发者来说 这有点太低级了
but it was a bit too low level
对于一般的开发者来说 这有点太低级了
for the general developers
因为当我们
because when we
有越来越多的初学者
had more and more beginners
开始尝试并采用视图时
starting to try and adopt view
我们意识到 好吧
we realized okay
他们没有兴趣去
they are not interested in
学习如何配置这些
learning how to configure these
比尔工具的破坏者
bunglers of Bill tools
而他们所关心的
and what they cared
他们关心的是要有一个公约 有一个启动点
about is to have a convention to have a starter point
以使事情迅速发展
to get things going quickly
所以在2015年
so in 2015
我创建了vuci
I created vuci
这是一个更高层次的工具链 专门用于查看
which is a higher level tool chain dedicated for view
建立在web pack的基础上
built on top of web pack
它可以做很多我们今天认为是标准的事情
it does many things we consider standard today
例如
for example
预先配置的
pre configured
这意味着人们需要的大多数常见功能
which means most common features one would need
都是开箱即用的 例如
should work out of the box like
今天你对V的期望是什么
what you would expect from v today
对 所以
right so
但是
but
为了获得这种配置
in order to get that kind of configuration
在玩网络包的基础上工作
working on top of playing web pack
实际上是一项大量的工作
is in fact a lot of work
并确保所有这些不同的选项
and making sure all these different options
比如你是否使用类型脚本
like whether you are using type script
以及你是否使用
and whether you are using
你使用的是哪个测试运行器
which test runner you are using
并确保所有这些
and making sure all
这些不同的
these different
选项的组合 可以一起工作
combinations of options that can work together
而不管你选择了什么选项
and no matter what options you've chosen
实际上是大量的工作
was in fact lot of work
它还配备了一个开发服务器
it also came with a dev server
带有热模块替换功能
with hot module replacement
带有自动组织的构建命令
build command with automatic organizations
它还包括现代模式 当你使用拔珠时 珠子就会为你服务
it also included the modern mode which bead kind of
当你使用珠子的时候 它是为你服务的
serves when you use bead plucking
遗留模式与V今天你得到
legacy with v today you get the
遗留模式
a legacy mode
当时在vci中被称为现代模式
back then in vci was called modern mode
它在默认情况下发送esm 然后再回落到
where it shipped esm by default and then falls back to
通过使用运行时的非 esm 捆绑格式
a non esm bundle format by using runtime
本地模块支持检测
native module support detection
所以在UCI之外 我们还看到
so outside of UCI we also saw
创建 reactap 为 react 启动了一个类似的行
create reactap which started a similar row for react
还有一个值得一提的就是parcel
and also worth mentioning is parcel
它是第一个建立的工具 开创了0
which was the first built tool to pioneer the 0
配置的概念
configuration concept
所以在这个时候
so around this time
我们开始看到一套
we were starting to see a set of
框架无关的惯例
framework agnostic conventions
这是一种融合性的
that's sort of convergent
今天 我们仍然可以看到 在v right
which we still see today in v right
例如 如何导入和处理CSS 如何
for example how to import and handle CSS how to
你希望资产如何工作
how you expect assets to work
你如何将你的
how you would combine your
运送你的静态资产
ship your static assets
与模板上的索引HDR
with templ index HDR on template
所以很多我们熟悉的东西
so a lot of the things that we're familiar with
这些早期生成的工具
these early generation tools
我们看到它们
we see them
本质上是在vtd中开箱工作的
essentially being working out of the box in vtd
然后用ES 2015
and then with es 2015
最后
finally
javascript有了自己的标准化模块系统
javascript got its own standardized module system
因此 这开始有点挑战
so this started somewhat challenging
过渡期
transition period
从
moving from
andum
the andum
共同的GS 一个非常零散的系统
the common GS a very fragmented system
试图向智能系统靠拢
trying to converge towards the sm
但是
but
到目前为止 这是一个相当痛苦的时期 对吗？
this has been a quite of painful period so far right
我们今天在技术上仍然处于这种状态
which we are still technically still in today
我们还没有完全达到 但是
we're still not quite fully there yet but
这是不可能的
that's out of the scofield this talk
在某种程度上是
in some way v
是一种努力 以
is an effort to
帮助生态系统向前发展并向ESM靠拢
help the ecosystem move forward and converge on esm
我们已经处理了很多与这些模型格式有关的错误
and we've dealt with a lot of bugs
与这些模型格式有关的错误
related to these model formats along the way
总之 ESM模块的意义在于
anyway the implication
的含义是 我们开始看到
of es modules is that we started to see
工具 这些工具是
tools that were
设计的工具
designed with es modules
首先 比如说roll up
first for example roll up
所以roll up是
so roll up was
第一个捆绑器 其设计的前提是
the first bundler that was designed with a premise of
将es模块作为
serving es module as the
唯一的标准模块格式
only standard module format
在这里 常见的js处理方式实际上已经加入了v
where common js handling has actually added on v
或摘取
or plucking
作为一个额外的功能
as an additional feature
所以Ronald作为es模块首先允许它是
so Ronald being es module first allowed it to be
让它的核心变得更简单、更有效
allowed its core to be simpler and more efficient
而且还释放了一些功能 比如
and also unlocked capabilities like
树的摇动
tree shaking
由于静态分析的作用
thanks to the static analysis
▪ es模块设计的友好性
friendliness of the design of es modules
但是 生态系统在湿包方面的投入非常大
but the ecosystem was so heavily invested in wet pack
而由于缺乏对热适度的支持
and due to the lack of support for hot moderate
辊筒的放置
placement for roll up
好吧 我们并没有真正看到一个更高层次的
alright we didn't really see a higher level
构建在Roll up之上的应用程序解决方案
app solution built on top of roll up
走向主流
going mainstream
你所看到的大多数主流解决方案都很好
most of the mainstream solutions you see next as great
反应UCI主要还是基于影响 因为
react UCI was mostly still impact based because
因为用户是如此的依赖一个替代者的数量
users are so reliant on how much a replacement
和webpack的方式 基本上能够处理
and the way that webpack was essentially able to handle
任何模块格式
any module format
甚至
even
有些模块只是
some of the modules were just
运送的
shipped
错了的混合格式
incorrectly with mixed formats
webpack仍然能够处理它们
webpack was still able to handle them
所以大多数用户使用
so most users use
卷起来 主要用于自定义设置或混杂的库
roll up mostly for custom setups or bungling libraries
所以在2017年
so in 2017
我们终于在浏览器中看到了原生的es模块
we finally saw native es modules in the browser
而没有
and without
所以这意味着我们现在可以在最近使用es模块 而无需
so this means we can now use es modules lately without
需要一个Bill步骤
the need of a Bill step
这一次 社区也开始承认
and this time the community also started to acknowledge
的
the
支付不断增长的注释模块的大小
paying of ever growing size of note modules
我们正在
we are
我们意识到 也许我们建立的一些工具
realizing okay maybe some of the tools that we built
太重了
were too heavy
一些我们建立的工具是
some of the tools we built were
可以更快
could be faster
这是因为
it was
因为
because
也许我们只是习惯了它的缓慢 也许是
maybe we just got used to the slowness of it maybe
可能有办法让它更快
there could be ways of making it faster
但与此同时
but at the same time
如果我们使用本地的是模块 并采用
if we go with native yes modules and go
无内置
builtless
但我们仍然习惯于很多东西
but we're still used to a lot of the things
但我们仍然习惯于很多东西 而这些东西的启用只是因为内置的工具
that were enabled only because of built tools
例如
for example
我们想使用
we want to use
单一文件组件
single file components
我们想使用transpire类型的脚本
we want to transpire type script
我们想使用gsx post CSS
we want to use gsx post CSS
都是好东西
are the goodstuff that
我们需要一个Bill步骤来处理这些问题
that we need a Bill step to deal with
对了 如果native vsm有一个转换API会怎么样？
right so what if native vsm had a transform API
这就是我所问的问题
that was the question that I was asking
好吧
well
所以我意识到也许它不需要这样做
and so I realized maybe it didn't need to
因为本地vs模块是通过GDP请求获取的
since native vs modules are fetched over a GDP request
所以
so
我们可以
we can
让开发服务器
let a dev server
进行任何需要的转换
perform whatever transform needed on the fly
并且该开发服务器会
and that dev server would
感觉
feel
和一个静态文件服务器很相似
quite similar to just a static file server
如果你考虑一下
if you think about it
静态文件服务器只是读取文件和
a static file server just reads the file and
感受到它的存在
sense it as is where
一个更聪明的开发服务器会读取一个typecript文件
a smarter dev server would read a typescript file
注意 它实际上并不是javascript
notice that it isn't actually javascript
所以它只是在提供服务之前将其转换为javascript
so it just transforms into javascript before serving it
对
right
所以
so
这完全可以做到
this could totally work
所以当我在寻找一个更轻的替代品时
so as I was searching for a lighter alternative to
speciali的轻量级替代品 因为我自己
speciali myself because I was
因为我有时厌倦了
sometimes fed up with
工具链的缓慢和沉重
the slowness and heaviness of the tool chain
我开始尝试这个想法
I started experimenting with this idea
所以在2019年3月
so in March 2019
我创建了一个概念验证的观察器
I created a proof of concept observer
能够转换和加载一些
that was able to transform and load few
单一文件的组件
single file components over
本地ES模块导入
native es module imports
但是有两个主要问题我没有完全
however there were 2 major problems that I didn't quite
解决的问题
solve back then
所以第一个问题是
so the first is
如何处理MPM的依赖性
how to handle mpm dependencies
和第二个问题
and the second
第二个问题是 如何对这些模块进行多少替换？
is how to perform how much replacement over native
这些模块
these modules
当时我还在忙着做视图3的工作
I was also busy working on view 3 at the time
所以我没有真正继续这个项目
so I didn't really continue this poc
直到一年后
it was until a year later
当我要睡觉的时候
as I was going to bed
我突然有了这样的感悟
I suddenly had this epiphany of
如何在本地进行热马达替换
how to perform hot motor replacement over native
本机ESM
native esm
我记不清楚了
I can't remember exactly
如何
how
为什么？
why
我想出了这个主意 也许是因为
I came up with the idea maybe because
使得这个Poc的工作是
making that poc work was
一直在我的脑海中 但一旦我有了这个想法 我就必须测试它
has always been at the back of my head but
一旦我有了这个想法 我就必须对它进行测试
once I had the idea I just had to test it out
所以我开始了黑客工作 一直工作到早上6点
so I started working hacking on it and worked until 6 a
上午6点
m in the morning
并得到了另一个概念验证的工作
and got another proof of concept working
这一次
this time
这一次是真正开始了V
this time it was the actual start of v
所以这一次我得到了
so this time I got
一个深度服务器 能够
a depth server that was
能够改变一个视图的单一最终组件
able to transform a view single final component
在飞行中
on the fly
它还能在原生的ESM上处理热马达的替换
it also handle hot motor replacement over native esm
第二天 第一个版本就出来了
so the very first release came out the next day
有一个非常粗糙的硬编码逻辑
with a very crude hardcode logic
那就是只支持视图组件 对吗？
that is that supported only view components right
最初的意图是让它
the initial intention was for it
成为一个轻量级的vcli替代品
to be a lightweight vcli alternative
所以下一步就是要从概念验证
so the next step was to move from proof
概念到更多的结构
concept to a more Sierra structure
所以我做了一些研究
so I did some research
并发现了web dev server
and found out about web dev server
这也是一个无捆绑式的服务器
which was also a bundless step server
我认为
I think
我认为它当时被称为esdav服务器
I think it was caught esdav server back then
现在被称为web slash dev server
which is now caught at web slash dev server
因此 由于我的主要兴趣是
so since my main interest was
在使
in making
热蒙太奇替换在Nadi vsm上工作
hot montage replacement work over nadi vsm
我实际上考虑将
I actually considered making
的中间件
v to just the middleware for esdav
服务器的中间件 因为我看到了它
server after I saw it
但是
but
深入了解一下
looking deeper into it
我还想让vj成为一个更高层次的
I also had the vision for vj to be a higher level
开箱即用的体验
out of the box experience
就像vuci和parcel一样 在某些方面
like vuci and parcel in some way
所以让它成为一个只有Dampserver的中间产品 只是
so making it a middlewear of only a dampserver just
显得很有局限性
seem to limiting overall
所以我最终
so I ended up
使用一个基于coa的服务器设置 其灵感来自于
using a coa based server setup which was inspired by
esdf服务器
esdf server
而最初的实现是 每个
and the initial implementation was that each
插件
plugging
将
would
被实现为一个co a中间件
be implemented as a co a middleware
所以视图转换逻辑
so the view transform logic
视图插件将是一个中间件
the view plugging would be a middleware
共同的中间件
co a middleware
因此 2天后
so 2 days
2天后 我得到了热模块的替换
2 days later I got the hot module replacement
也为平面js工作
also working for plane js
这很重要 因为
which was important because
热模块的火焰只适用于视图组件 显然
hot module flames only for view components obviously
并不是
isn't
将会是非常有用的
going to be super useful
我们还需要处理通用的javascript逻辑
we also need to handle generic javascript logic
此外 还需要处理MPM的依赖性
and in addition for handling mpm dependencies
我选择使用snow pack v第一版 所以
I opted to use snow pack v version one so
现在是作为es安装 所以
which is now now as es install so
雪包的第一个版本实际上是一个
version one of snow pack was in fact a
预先配置好的卷起
pre configured roll up
工具 能够转换
tool that is able to convert
npm包 不管它是什么格式的
npm packages no matter what format it is in
转换成可以在浏览器中运行的es模块
into es modules that could run in the browser
所以这就解决了问题 因为对
so this solve the problem because right
因为最大的问题
because the biggest problem
问题是
problem is that
我们有一个非常零散的模块系统
we have this very fragmented module system
有些模块是在umd
where some modules are in umd
一些模块在公共js中
something in common js
一些是ESM
something esm
好吧 所以我们需要把它们规范化
all right so we need to normalize them
变成同样的esm格式 可以在浏览器中运行
into the same esm format that can run in the browser
and snow pack
如果你想达到这个目的
if you want to serve that purpose
所以
so
然后在0.5版本中 我
and then in 0.5 I was
能够登陆一个滚子供电的饲料建立
able to land a roller powered feed built
我决定仍然使用Bono进行生产
I decided to still use the Bono for production
因为obano的部署仍然是很棘手的
because obano deployment is still tricky to get right
我们在船坞里解释了这个问题
we explain this in the docks
我还用卷起的方式代替湿包
I also use roll up instead wet pack
因为卷起是更多的ESM第一
because roll up is more esm first
因此 它与 "V "的关系要好得多
so it lines much better with
与V的关系更好
better with v
事实上 在当时
in fact back then
我相信湿包仍然无法输出
I believe wet pack was still not able to output
直接的ES模型
direct es models
所以从
so from the
另一个角度来看
other perspective
脚也有点开始变成这样了
feet also kind of started to becoming this
炙手可热的替代者Def Silver for rollum
hot replacement def silver for rollum
对 所以它成为一种互补的关系
right so it becomes a complementary relationship
现在 在这一点上
now at this point
大部分的主要问题都得到了回答
most of the major questions have been answered
但我也想验证一下
but I also wanted to validate
是否
whether
这些采摘和API
these plucking and API
设计是否足够灵活
design is flexible enough
为更高的解决方案提供动力
to power even higher solutions
特别是
especially
在我所提供的服务的情况下
in the scenario of service I rendering
如果人们想在它上面建立
what if people want to build
元框架的情况下
meta frameworks on top of it
对
right
所以在视图生态系统中
so in the view ecosystem
我们有一个静态侧生成器账户view press
we had a static side generator account view press
许多用户喜欢它
which many users liked
它允许你编写
it allows you to write
文件基础路由与标记文件
file base routing with markup files
而且你可以在其中发明一些组件
and you can invent few components in it
而它只是为你生成文件
and it just generates documentations for you
它使用视图服务器端的渲染能力
it uses views serverside rendering capabilities
所以它把markdown解析成一个视图组件
so it parses markdown into a view component
然后把它编译成
then compiles it
作为一个视图组件 然后运行它
as a view component and then run it
在ssr期间运行它来生成静态HTML
during ssr to generate the static HTML
然而 视图印刷机是基于湿式包装的
however view press was wet pack based
而在大型项目中 启动开发服务器可能需要
and in larger projects it could take
要花很长的时间来启动开发服务器
a very long time to start the dev server
而一次编辑可能需要
and a single edit could take
体现为热修改或替换
seconds to be reflected with hot mod or replacement
所以我想用一个类似的系统来看看
so I wanted to see with a similar system
但基于视图
but based on view
我们可以在DX方面获得多大的改进
how much improvement we can get in terms of DX
所以我创造了小麦压榨机
so I created wheat press
一个以小麦为动力的静态侧发电机
a wheat powered static side generator
这是与小麦本身平行开发的
this was developed in parallel with wheat itself
所以你可以看到日期是在小麦0.5版发布后的几天
so you can see the date is like a few days after
0.5版本的小麦
0.5 release of wheat
而今天 它为v
and today it powers the documentation for both v
和vgas的文档
and vgas its themselves
所以
so
重要的
the important
在这整个过程中 电子新闻的重要作用是 它是
role of e press during this whole process is that it's
作为一个实验场
served as an experiment field
为银色渲染API设计
for silver rendering API design
和一些内部的API变化
and some of the internal API changes
包括插入式API的设计
including the plugging API design
在v的早期版本中
in the early versions of v
因此 当我在开发 v press
so as I was working on v press
我有1
I have 1/1 hand experience of okay
这就是我所需要的，如果我在vip的基础上建立一个更高级的
this is what I need if I were building a higher
的基础上建立一个更高层次的工具。
level tool on top of v
所以它也
so it also
让我能够考虑到正确的
allows me to think about the right level of the
抽象的正确水平，我应该暴露
abstraction should I expose
那么我应该暴露多少呢？
so how much should I expose
如果你暴露的太多
if you expose too much
你就有可能使用法变得超级复杂。
you risk making the the usage superfer bows and complex
但如果你暴露的不够多，那么
but if you don't expose enough then
你就不可能建立起真正有用的东西
you won't be able to build actually something useful
对，所以要找到平衡点
right so finding the balance
为了找到这个平衡点
in order to find the balance
我必须在每个发现的基础上自己建立一些东西。
I had to build something myself on top of each find up
所以
so
接下来就是漫长的磨练，以达到一个点。
what followed was the long grind to reach one point
哦，我的目标是用ucli进行功能模仿
oh I was aiming for feature parody with ucli
而且我们的用户也越来越多
and we were also getting more users and
随着用户的增加，我们得到了更多的bug
with more users we got a lot more bugs
大多数的bug都与以下方面有关
most of the bugs were related to
下一个模块的格式与mpm的依赖关系，优化器
next module formats with mpm dependencies the optimizer
有问题
having issues
还有很多小的错误被修复了。
and a lot of small bugs fixed along the way
所以
so
在2020年4月至11月期间
between April and November 2020
我转移
I shift
91个版本
91 releases
一路上升到
all the way up to
一个点 o r c
one point o r c
9，但孪生点o从未真正借给它，所以
9 but the twin point o never actually lend it so
之所以如此
the reason for that
因为当我为一个点工作时
was because as I worked towards one point
我意识到Ved的作用远远超过了
I realized ved can be much more
不仅仅是Ucli的替代品
than just a replacement of ucli
它可以是2个方面
it could be 2 things
首先，它可以是一个与框架无关的
first is that it could be a framework agnostic
动物配置的工具，为终端用户提供类似
animal config built tool for end users something like
所以这本质上是一个
so this was essentially a
更加通用的视图CI
more generic view ci
我们的目标是让每个框架都能...
the goal is so that each framework should be able to um
可以把这个框架的特定逻辑封装在
can encapsulate this framework specific logic
在一个单一的插件中
in a single plugin
然后你就可以
and then you would
其他大部分的
most of the other
共同分享的功能应该是开箱即用的
common share features should just work out of the box
为终端用户服务
for end users
第二种是
the second is
一个共享调整层
a share tuning layer
为框架作者提供的
for framework authors
以便
so that
编写下一个或拼写孩子的人
people working on next or spell kids
或者是这个的下一个
or maybe the next next to this
可以
could
能够
be
能够利用我们在V中所做的一些工作
able to leverage some of the work we've done in v
的工作，这样他们就不需要重新发明轮子了
so that they don't need to reinvent the wheels
这样我们就可以把重点放在差异化的功能上
so that we can focus on the differentiating features
这样
that
我们专注于创新
we focus on the innovations
而不是
instead
而不是一遍又一遍地重新发明同样的轮子
the reinvents in the same wheels over and over again
所以我决定
so I decided to
工作重写
work rewrite
以实现这些目标
ved completely in order to fulfill these goals
因此，vitu在2020年12月开始完成重写。
so vitu was complete rewrite started in December 2020
其中一些主要目标是
some of the main goals were
首先，我们想让构架师变得更加实用。
first we want to go framer gagmastic
我们选择了一个通用的角色
we opted for a universal role up
兼容的插入式API
compatible plugging API
灵感来自于hamr，它是
inspired by hamr which is
由杰森-米拉德作者preact创建
created by Jason millard author preact
我们还采用了一个新的ssr运行时间
we also adopted a new ssr runtime
它的灵感来自Stout kit和
which was inspired by stout kit and
首次出现
first appeared
所以Rich Harris创造了
so rich Harris created
在早期的spell kit中创建了这个，然后
created this in early spell kit and then
fret移植到snow pack，然后我们移植到wheat。
fret ported to snow pack and then we ported to wheat
而且我们还改用了一个
and we also switch to a
是的，溢出的动力依赖性预捆绑系统
yes spilled powered dependency pre bundling system
这
which
这使得整个依赖关系的处理快了一百倍
made the whole dependency handling hundred times faster
最后在16年2月
and finally in February 16
我们发布了一个V
we shipped a v
到
to
所以这就是
so that was
左右。
about
所以12月7日到2月16日
so December 7 to February 16th
3个月多一点，所以我认为
a bit over 3 months so I think
重写是比较快的
the rewrite was relatively fast
因为我们已经学到了很多
because we already learned a lot
我们修复了很多东西，现在已经达到了一个点
we fixed a lot of things on the way to one point now
而且我有足够的时间来
and I got enough time to
我也有足够的时间去思考如何调整事情的结构
also think along the way of how to restructure things
也有更好的办法
better to be too
所以在
so after
vitu发布
vitu released
这在技术上是
which was technically the
实际的一个点哦，对了
actual one point oh right
我打算将
I plan to move
我打算把一些焦点移回视图上，因为
some of the focus back to the view because
我把这么多的时间放在VT上，而在工作中
I put so much timing to VT while working on
对一点O和二点O
towards one point o and 2 point o
所以我需要把一些爱还给视图
so I need to give some love back to view
所以我需要在运出后给视图一些爱。
after its shipped
我还想确保
I also want to make sure
即使我在两个项目之间分配时间，Ved也可能被维护。
ved can be probably maintained even if I split time
也要确保Ved能够维持下去，即使我在这两个项目之间分配时间
between the 2 projects
所以我知道只有在我们有一个T的情况下才有可能。
so I knew it could only be possible if we have a t
所以
so
我这样做了，我创建了一个讨论主题
I did and I created a discussion thread
提名了几个最初的团队成员，今天
nominated a few initial team members and today
今天，大部分的日常维护工作都是
the majority of daily maintenance is
今天，大部分的日常维护都是由我们的团队成员完成的
performed by our team members
和我们最新的3点O主要版本的团队合作
and the team with our latest 3 point o major release
主要由团队努力推动
mainly driven by team efforts
我想在此向团队表示感谢
I would like to give a big shout out to the team
特别是Matius
in in particular matius
他们一直在做一个惊人的工作
who have been doing a phenomenal job
在推动V的发展
in pushing v forward
我也
I'm also
非常非常感谢
very very grateful
我也非常感谢那些围绕着 "泄露 "而形成的令人难以置信的社区。
to the incredible community that has formed around
泄露的
leaked
我们看到许多框架作者
we're seeing many frameworks authors
积极合作
actively collaborating with the
提供反馈
providing feedback
并分享关于我们如何能更好地
and sharing ideas on how we can better
作为一个评论层
serve as a commentating layer
看到这么多令人振奋的新方向，真是令人惊讶和鼓舞。
truly amazing and inspiring to see so many exciting new
的项目正在探索的方向
directions being explored by ved powered projects
我很荣幸地看到你们都在这里
and I am honored to have you all here
在这个会议上分享网站
sharing sites at this conference
所以我希望你们能享受其余的会谈内容
so I hope you enjoy the rest of the talks
谢谢
thank you